RG 056, Connecticut Tercentenary Commission
Connecticut State Library
Tercentenary Commission of the State of Connecticut records
1928-1959
bulk 1929-1936
Connecticut State Library
Tercentenary Commission of the State of Connecticut
14 cubic feet
The General Assembly created this commission in 1929 to plan for the commemoration of the 300th anniversary of Connecticut’s settlement.
RG056
Multiple
Historical Note
The General Assembly created this commission in 1929 to plan for the commemoration of the 300th anniversary of Connecticut’s settlement. The Commission expanded from seven members, headed by Dr. G.C.F. Williams, to eleven, supported by an executive secretary, Herbert L. Crapo, and staff. It created several subcommittees to conduct work. Samuel H. Fisher was Chairman after January 4, 1934. Its program included publications, exhibits, public ceremonies, musical events, pageants, parades, school activities, an industrial exhibit, religious observances, and the sale of medals, plates, and auto tags. Twenty-two information bureaus were established, and many localities organized their own related programs. The Henry Whitfield House in Guildford received a donation for its restoration. The final exercises took place on October 11, 1935, and the commission wound up its work on June 30, 1936.
Scope and Content
The record group contains minutes of meetings of the Commission, its executive committee, and subcommittees, administrative, personnel, and financial records, scrapbooks, photographs, postcards and files about local celebrations, reports of public libraries, music, local history material, much of which was assembled by Connecticut school children, and visitors’ registers.
Related Material
, Connecticut State Library.
, Connecticut State Library.
RG 012, Records of the Connecticut State Library, Box 73, Tercentenary Commission, 1935 - 1936.
, Connecticut State Library.
RG 064, Picture Group 360, Connecticut Tercentenary Celebration, 1935.
, Connecticut State Library.
RG 169, Clubs and Private Organizations, Accession 2001-077, Wethersfield Tercentenary Committee, 1929-1934.
The book collections contain various materials published by the Commission or by others in connection with the Tercentenary observance. Included are the
Report to the Governor, 1936 June 30,
and the sixty "Historical Publications Series" pamphlets.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Tercentenary Commission of the State of Connecticut
Persons:
Williams, George Clinton Fairchild, 1857-; Fisher, Samuel H. (Samuel Herbert), b. 1867; Crapo, Herbert L.
Subjects:
Tercentenary Commission of the State of Connecticut -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut -- History; Connecticut -- Centennial celebrations, etc
Document Types:
Correspondence; Minutes; Photographs; Financial records; Scrapbooks; Clippings; Reports; Registers (lists); Postcards
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The records were turned over to the State Library some time after the Commission completed its work on June 30, 1936. Judge William Maltbie held some of the records first. A note in the files stated that a major part of the records - "mostly correspondence" - were discarded in 1959. A motion picture film, "Three Hundred Years of Connecticut Life and Industry," was destroyed by the Archives in July 1973.
Container List
- Records, 1928-1959
  - T002716
    - 1. Minutes of meetings, 1929 May-1936 June (Box 1-2)
      Typed and mimeographed copies of meetings of the Commission and its Executive Committee (3 binders) and many of its subcommittees (2 binders).
    - 2. Lists of files and property, 1936-1959 (Box 2)
      Several lists of files, equipment and property disposed of when the Commission disbanded.
    - 3. Record of local celebrations, 1935-1936 (Box 2)
      Compiled by Margaret M. Allardyce, Recording Secretary.
    - 4. Memoranda by A.R. Rogers, Director of Celebration, 1935 January-July (Box 2)
      "Reports to Mr. Fisher," chair of the Commission, containing suggestions, plans and comments.
    - 5. Reports on library activities, 1935-1936 (Box 3)
      Form reports from public libraries concerning their tercentenary celebration activities.
    - 6. Papers of the Committee on Historic Sites and Markers, 1934-1935 (Box 3)
    - 7. Southington Committee papers, 1935 (Box 3)
    - 8. Photographs of Tercentenary activities, 1935-1936; Mounted, uncaptioned prints, two albums (Box 3)
    - 9. Postcards of historical buildings and sites (Box 4)
    - 10. Stamp and medal designs (Box 4)
      Drawings and photographs.
    - 11. Music (Box 4)
    - 12. Certificates (Box 4)
      Blank certificates to honor those assisting the tercentenary celebration.
    - 13. Files on sale of motor vehicles plates, 1935 (Box 4)
      Correspondence and notes of Mr. George Beebe.
    - 14. Payrolls and related materials, 1935 (Box 4-6)
      Form Emergency Relief Administration project payrolls and related reports, correspondence and memoranda.
    - 15. Budget and accounting papers, 1931-1936 (Box 6-7)
      Final statements, budget statements, petty cash book, medal accounts, etc.
    - 16. Local history materials, 1933-1935 (Box 8)
      Reports, essays, worksheets, questionnaires and other papers on Connecticut local history, many compiled by school children, collected through the State Board of Education for the tercentenary.
    - 17. Visitors' registers, 1935; 27 volumes
      Signatures of visitors to the information booths and to the State House and State Library.
      - New London, 1935 July 3-October 14 (Volume Volume 1)
      - Danbury, 1935 July 10-October 14 (Volume Volume 2)
      - Norwalk, 1935 July 3-October 13 (Volume Volume 3)
      - Norwalk, 1935 June 23-October 10 (Volume Volume 3B)
      - Granby, 1935 July 18-October 3 (Volume Volume 4)
      - Norwich, 1935 July 4-October 12 (Volume Volume 5)
      - Danielson, 1935 July 3-October 5 (Volume Volume 6)
      - Westport, 1935 July 3-October 12 (Volume Volume 7A)
      - Westport, 1935 July 3-September (Volume Volume 7B)
      - Fairfield, 1935 June 18-September 25; 1 volume (Volume Volume 8)
      - Fairfield, 1935 September 26-October 15; 1 volume (Volume Volume 8)
      - New Haven, 1935 July 2-October 11 (Volume Volume 9)
      - Ridgefield, 1935 June 26-October 14 (Volume Volume 10)
      - Enfield, 1935 July 2-October 10 (Volume Volume 11)
      - Windsor, 1935 July 2-September 27 (Volume Volume 12)
      - Stafford Springs, 1935 July 2-October 5 (Volume Volume 13)
      - Greenwich, 1935 (Volume Volume 14)
      - Simsbury, 1935 July 8-October 15 (Volume Volume 15)
      - Saybrook, 1935 July 15-October 14 (Volume Volume 16)
      - Putnam, 1935 July 18-October 7 (Volume Volume 17)
      - Winsted, 1935 August 1-October 5 (Volume Volume 18)
        Includes one loose paper that notes several items for sale at the celebration.
      - Canaan, 1935 August 5-October 3 (Volume Volume 19)
      - Library booth, 1935 July 2
      - Litchfield, 1935
      - Memorial Hall (State Library), 1935 October 11
      - Old State House, 1935 May 5-October 26
      - Room 103 (State Library), 1935 July 3-October 24
    - 18. Scrapbooks, 1928-1936; 7 volumes
      Contains newspaper and magazine clippings, postcards, programs, and memorabilia.
      - Commission Scrapbooks, circa 1928-1935; 2 volumes
        Activities of the Commission.
        - 1928 December 29-1935 October 13 (Volume Volume 1)
        - 1934 August-1935 October 13 (Volume Volume 2)
      - Local activities, circa 1929-1936; 5 volumes
        Organized by town.
        - Ansonia-Franklin (Volume Volume 1)
        - Glastonbury-Litchfield (Volume Volume 2)
        - Madison-Scotland (Volume Volume 3)
        - Seymour-Windsor (Volume Volume 4)
        - Windsor Locks-Woodstock (Volume Volume 5)
  - 1999-049
    - 19. Connecticut Tercentenary pageant, 1635-1935, Stony Creek, (Branford), 1935 April 27 (Box 1)
      Pageant script and photographs.